Don’t blame yourself. That’s your problem.
Yesterday I told you to say that I’m not guilty.
It’s just a joke you are enjoying,
you are just playing
guilts with yourself
when you say that.
Because you like to play such
terrible jokes with yourself.
Don’t say that you are guilty at all.
By saying that, you see, you are trying to
enjoy a sort of a sadism
against yourself.
You are against your Self.
Self, that is your Spirit.
That's what it feels like.It feel like um..
It’s not a good thing.
It is not what is wanted.
It's not that is desired for you.
So, just don’t play on it.
Whatever are your moods are not
correct, it should not be there.
By your moods, you are lost!
Sometimes you get this mood,
sometimes you get another
mood of aggression.
You are in a temper or
something like that.
And sometimes you get into this
kind of absolute elated mood.
Both are useless, absolutely.
Just throw them away.
Why  should we do that?
Both are mythical.
[unclear]
Yes, the positivity, also the so-called
positivity, means aggression on others.
You start showing your
aggression on others.
You can aggress others, also.
That's even worse.
[unclear] love and happiness…
That’s, that’s the thing I was saying.
Be joyous, be happy for
what God has given you.
Watch the birds in the morning time.
See the flowers in the morning time,
what do they have?
They are standing in the sun, in the rain,
they are facing the nature all the time.
Imagine the delicate
petals of the flowers,
do they show any signs of
negativity or of aggression?
They only emit fragrance.
Till they live, they will emit fragrance,
if they will die, they're not bothered.
Aggressive person, cannot
come to Sahaja Yoga!
They cannot  go very far.
Neither a negative person! But
aggressive cannot. He'll drop out.
Sahaja Yoga recedes from such people.
You have to be humble,
but you are not to be slaves!
In extremes, at least one should
know the difference between the two.
If there are extremes –
say something is very black,
then you can see the white
very clearly against it.
When you know how to move from
one extreme to another extremes,
you should be able to see
both the things very clearly.
And that’s how you come to the centre.
Maybe it is for your
own good to be like that.
You may say – ‘Yes, we understand
Mother, but we can’t do it.
You can!
You just watch yourself
and see how it works,
how your mind is working.
It’s your horse, you have to master it!
You are supposed to be a rider,
and the horse is taking you
somewhere, wherever it feels like;
either to negativity, or go to the positivity,
so called, doing the aggressiveness.
It is the horse that is leading
you, not you are leading the horse.
What kind of a rider it is?
And the horse is like a pendulum,
and you are led by it.
Then, when you identify
yourself with that horse,
you think what you do it is happening.
You can control it.
You have to tell yourself
that is to tell your mind to behave itself,
otherwise you people cannot
go very deep into Sahaja Yoga.
You have to go much deeper.
If you are worried about
superficialities, you cannot go deeper.
Deep down is the truth, there lies all the joy.
All the trees, all living things,
have their roots deep down.
Find out your roots, where are they?
They are all imbedded in
your heart, in your Spirit.
Nothing [unclear,] your superficial thing, where
your mind is moving like a wind here and there
just like a dead leaf.
If a big train is coming,
and the train is faced,  say with the,
some sort of an
obstacle, it cannot stop.
But if there is a little worm
and if it wants to save
itself from the train, it can.
It can hide itself or something.
You are not a worm,
you are a human being.
A little living thing can do that much.
You are a human being,
and if you cannot stop
yourself from your destruction,
then who can stop you?
You see the nature,
people live together.
Tiger lives in a forest
and there are many
creatures who exist.
But if human beings
cannot save themselves,
with all the brain that they have [unclear]
with all the energy that they have,
with all the discoveries
that they have made,
then who is going to save oneself?
Either you aggress on
others, or you kill yourself.
And then what should Mataji do?
What should anyone do
under these circumstances?
But to make you face it.
In Sahaja Yoga, you can
face it very clearly.
You can see others doing it also.
But first you must see it in yourself.
Unless and until you see it in yourself,
what you are doing to yourself,
you cannot see in others.
When I say, "You see it in
yourself," you became self-centred.
I mean, anything you
say, can be twisted.
When I say, "You
see it in yourself,"
that means, you detach
yourself and see in yourself.
What is your mind doing?
That’s how you can learn others.
Also, that they are doing the same.
Like, a person – say,
is fond of good food
Alright!
If he can see that he is
hankering after good food,
all the time he is
thinking about food,
his mind is working like that,
if he can see that, he can
correct it also, if he can see it.
Apart from that, when he
sees somebody doing it,
he would not hate that person,
but he would help him to cure.
On the contrary, I have seen
those who are like that
hate the other person,
make fun of the other person
while they have the same weakness.
Why, why it happens? There
is a psychology behind it.
Because that one which is
doing like this wrong in him,
you hate that one in you,
subconsciously,
and that’s what you hate in others.
But that is consciously.
If you hate that part in you consciously,
there wouldn’t be any problem!
That part which is negative,
the part that is telling
you all these things,
the part that misleads you,
the part that spoils you,
the part that covers the Self you see,
in you,
if you could manage to see that,
and say "No, not that part."
No.
But, then you start despising the whole.
It’s a very subtle thing.
Either you move from
this side to that side,
if I try to push you, you just go
like a sprint to the other end.
When I have to push on that side, like
a sprint you go to the other end.
The thing is, the basic thing is that
the extremes are to be avoided.
This is the basic point,
is extremes to be avoided.
If you feel you are getting negative,
take a shoe, beat yourself nicely.
Go out and shout,
or take a pillow
and hit it hard. Alright?
But if you are negative inside,
what you will do, you will
go and beat your wife
or beat your husband;
whatever may be the case.
It’s a very simple thing
for a Sahaja Yogi to do,
is to be amused about yourself.
Just be amused, "Look at
this Mr. So-and-so."
Now see.
When you start seeing yourself like
that, you see, you’ll be amused at yourself.
"Now, so now, Mr. So-and-so
is coming up like this."
"Oh, come along, come
along. Now the vanity,
come along, I would like to
see the vanity that I am."
Seeing Mr. Ego coming up,
now, "Here Mr. Ego stand."
Then you'll start seeing.
Be amused about it in the real sense.
And you will be surprised that
these things will drop out.
[unclear]
Yes, yes, of course. Very much. Yes.
Yes.
No you should say, "Get a way.
You take two running jumps and go."
That will help.
If you want to have
phraseologies, I can tell you.
But I think you are
much more equipped
in English language with all
the beautiful humour that have,
you have.
Just play that on
yourself, you see.
Humour is a beautiful thing that
you can really play on to yourself.
Instead of playing these
melancholy sounds and
foolishly indulging into
all of this romantic nonsense.
Better play some humour on yourself,
sit down, repeat some humour
and enjoy the humour upon yourself!
It works wondrously.
And those who know how to laugh at
themselves are the best people.
This is what it is, and then
when you are meditating,
then you will find real diamonds sparkling.
All that was foolish is chiselled down,
and you see that beautiful
joy-giving Spirit
manifesting itself beautifully
when you are alone,
and all your worry, all your problems,
and all negativity and so-called
aggressiveness and everything
just disappears, and
you are one with that,
and you are seeing proof of that,
the brilliance that it is joy,
you are seeing and feeling
this dignity of that
and the joy of it; the
brilliance that is flowing,
just think if you are
the sun, and you come,
and you see the sun, I
mean the rays coming
and working it out and curing
and changing the colours,
and giving life.
Imagine!
How dignified you feel and
how beautiful you feel!
But you don’t feel vain about it.
If you are that, you just don’t
feel that there is something
special about it, you just see it.
Vanity comes when you
don’t have something.
When you have it, you say
‘it’s alright, it’s me,
it’s just flowing,
just watching  how
beautifully it is flowing."
Because of scientific research
in the psychological sphere,
this myth has come to us that if
we try to enjoy something like that,
then you become proud.
So, you just don’t enjoy. I mean
the sum total of the whole
thing in psychoanalysis
that you don’t enjoy anything in life.
In the sum total,
it counts too.
If it is not worked
with a Realised Soul,
with the compassion and love
and proper understanding,
it amounts to that!
That you just don’t
enjoy anything in life.
You analyse everything this way
you are bad, that way you are bad.
This way you are wrong,
that way you are wrong.
So, you are wrong completely.
You should be finished,
you are good for nothing,
useless, thrown away.
End up in the lunatic asylums,
or in some another wretched place
which is not meant for
human habitation at all.
Idiotic it is, I must say. Stupid!
It is like a
we call it in Marathi ‘dhoopatni’
Dhoopatni is a thing we use for
burning the incense, you see?
It is hollow on this side, and
hollow on the other side also,
because the one side is the stand, the
other side is where you put the incense.
So, you take that ‘dhoopatni’ and
you ask for something, you see.
Something is giving on this cup, you
turn it around for the other side.
So, the other side face him,
but this side, that is filled in, is gone, so you
go to see...  you want to see the other side now,
that what is left in the other
one. There is nothing is left,
all together. It’s finished
So it is said that, "Happy Dhoopatni "
means, the dhoopatni is that thing,
is given to you in the hand.
So, first you see this side, you
try to feel the joy in the cup.
Alright. Then you turn it around
to feel the other side of it.
But this side you have to receive it,
and the other side is the [unclear].
So, you need not go to the
right then to the left.
By the time you go to the
left, the right is over,
and the right side you run
up too,  the left is over.
Just be in the centre!
Push yourself in the centre,
just be there.
See the silence!
The silence of joy crawls in.
What’s it? What happened?
Sebastian was sleeping.
That’s the best!
He was breathing beautifully.
Unclear
That is the best, you
see. To sleep off.
Now, any questions?
What’s it?
How far should we be
concern with other people…
I mean in certain situations [unclear],
we should have a better understanding
Ya,  [unclear]
I would say, you see,  with this,
that you have wisdom.
All of you have your, wisdom.
And you tell them in a way
that you, "carry the
coal," as they say.
Because if you tell
somebody – “you are stupid”
I mean he will make hell for you.
He better not do that.
Alright.
Now, if you tell somebody
that, “you are very clever”
when he is stupid,
if he is really
[unclear]
Yes, they will know that, too. Because
people here are very clever! You see!
They are stupid in their wisdom,
but understanding that
what others are talking and
all that, they know very well!
So, the best thing is, whenever
you have to work on them,
work on them secretly.
Give them a bandhan,
give them shoe-beating,
but openly you give them tea.
Give them some vibrated salt.
vibrated, of course, of
course, of course, of course.
Keep Mataji’s photograph
and the candle there,
and then invite, give them tea,
give them some chanas.
You see, that’s how you have
to work with these people,
because they don’t understand this.
They may be clever,
so, give them some chana.
When they want, to have some
water, give them vibrated water.
So you work through their stomachs.
Now, when they start
arguing, avoid arguing
very wisely.
I think Rustom knows some things,
tricks like that. He does that.
He avoids talking about things.
I’ve seen him,
and I do it the most of all, I mean,
I’m very good at getting out of things.
When Gavin does it, is to keep quiet.
That’s...  there are ways and
methods by which you just
nail it through.
Sahaja Yoga methods are very different
from normal methods that you [unclear].
And these are miraculous methods.
The best thing if you want
to deal with someone,
you just leave it to Me,
and just tell “Mataji
please look after him.”
And then you will see the results
how he comes back to the normal.
You see, many things work out like that,
as I told you, the other
day we had gone to Crawley,
and there was a big myth
created, you see, sort of
a complete opposition
to Mataji was created,
and one man poor thing fighting
for Me and sort of thing.
And when we went to the
hall, all of them were
towards Mataji, absolutely and the
fellow was again put on the pedestal
and higher of that it was put.
Because some newspaper people came
asking for his name, for his
interview, and all that.
And he was amazed that
how, how they came?
He doesn’t know why they came to
take there an interview from him?
So, leave it to miracles,
as they say, “leave it to Geeves.”
You see this building reminds me.
You see, this is "leaving it
to Geeves."  This has worked.
You see, this building  itself is....
like these people came
and yesterday you met.
You must write down all these things
in a diary, I think you people should!
They went to Weston-super-Mare and
they all wanted to stay
in Weston-super-Mare,
and there was no place
for them, no place.
And they did not know what to do?
And they went all the way from here,
where to go? What to do?
They wanted to do camping,
I said, "No, no. Camping is
not allowed for my children."
So they went down to Bristol,
to a college to meet a Sahaja yogi,
and he organised for them, he offered himself,
he said, “Mataji, they can come and stay with us."
And there was another building just like this,
and they very nicely like lords they lived.
So, depend on the miracles
and the angels.
They are right here. All of
them, attending on to you.
Just here, all here,
and you watch for the miracles.
But we should be surrendered.
If you are not, then no.
You’ll be amazed how
the miracles work out!
And those who are closer and closer,
they would be amazed the
way things are worked out!
I mean, there are
so many things that like that. [unclear]
You should write a diary
of all these things,
what has happened and how.
Somebody must start it.
Even this place is nothing but that!
Yesterday, I just was thinking
where you could be, and
I hope you are happy [unclear].
I felt that you are all very happy.
I was wondering, "They
must have gone somewhere."
After all, you have to go on the war!
War front! This is the war here,
but in a very comfortable way.
And you are fighting them!
This place has something
which is to be fought out.
So, you are sent here.
Also many to fight.
A lot of past of England is here,
which is to be fought, and
that’s how you are here.
But in comfort.
You’ll be taken to the right
places where you have to fight,
but fight in comfort.
Angels are there,
and they want to
work through you!
So they’ll give you all the comfort.
You see, like a camera that we take
somewhere. You see, we keep it in proper places.
We may have difficulties in handling
it, and standing somewhere,
but the camera doesn’t
have any problem.
We must look after the camera
because it’s a delicate stuff.
Like that, you are the instruments.
So they look after you,
you are not tortured,
you are not troubled. But I mean,
supposing you get some kinks
in your head, then nobody can help you.
That’s a different point.
That’s your style
is to get kinks in the heads.
But otherwise, it’s
a very comfortable place!
And you are fighting, and you
don’t know that you are fighting!
You don’t know what
you are doing here!
You think, you are just
sitting and enjoying yourself.
You are doing great
work sitting down here!
The whole history of
England is fought here.
Better now?
And I was so happy that so
many of you agreed to come.
If I tell you this, don’t be
frightened for next time.
So, how far you have to go with others
is your sense of judgement,
and you learn this tact.
There are angels around you.
They will put your hand through it,
they will make you receive it
tell what, how to do.
That you should get thirty
people for Sahaja Yoga,
is something remarkable.
I had one person to
begin with in India.
One person! One old
lady of sixty years.
You are lucky people, I must say.
Already things are arranged
because when she told Me that there
was like a shop, you see, everybody is
telling them about yourself and all that, and
there is one, some Raja yogis came,
they never appeared and there were TM
people, of course they are out now.
It’s so.
It’s all worked out beforehand.
I mean, imagine this place to be
found out by Don.
Where ever you are, you
are spreading light,
you do not know about
it, but it is there.
Only keep your lanterns clean,
don’t get to kinks and waste
My energy for nothing at all.
And you will be amazed how
much light you are emitting,
and how much you are fighting,
and how many people
you are impressing!
So, you will be amazed that if
you leave it to Sahaja Yoga,
after some time you will just give up.
If you do not like a certain
thing, you just give up,
and you will not be bothered,
and neither you will be sorry.
Like I have seen My grandchildren, you
see, they come and work on somebody,
for a while they'll climb
on, and they will do this,
and they work very
hard, and it’s cling on,
but after some time they just get away.
Absolutely, all of them will leave just
like the dogs, you see, leave the bone.
In the same way, this bone is left now
nothing more can be done. They get out .
It happens like that, spontaneously.
Then you don’t even feel sorry
that you have not done anything,
"Oh you worked so hard, it
is such a waste" and all that.
You don’t think all these things.
You say, "Now we've done."
"Let it be."
But so many people, whom you will
think you have left, will come back.
What’s it?
The tea and coffee is
ready for everyone.
Alright. [unclear],
we have to go there.
We can bring it to You. But, I
think, most of us we have to …
Alright, then go ahead.
Better offer tea.
May God bless you!
for example supposing you say
you are a Buddhist, supposing.
One says, "I'm a buddhist."
You don't become a Buddha
by any chance at all.
And this understanding goes on
disappearing after sometime,
you see, among human beings.
And I was amazed that
really the head of the Zen
is not a realised soul
and I told him, but he told me
they had only 26 kashapas so far.
Only 26 realised souls they had
And he was travelling with about
500 disciples when he came to India
and none of them were
realised is a fact.
You see, now supposing you are an Indian
and if I tell here to someone that
in India if you go, these temples
are now being
a fortress of tantrics
and people are using the temples
which have living deities
there's something wrong with
these, people won't like.
But it's a fact!
If you go there, you'll be amazed
You see I could speak to them about these
things because they had invited Me for this.
I explained to them what is real
and I told them what
your temples mean
and how you go into thoughtless
awareness and all that.
But, first thing is realisation.
without that nothing happens, you see,
it is all prescribed for realised souls,
Zen, Zen means 'dyan' meditation.
Those who are not meditating,
means who are not realised
cannot understand Zen at all.
You are to be meditating.
Otherwise it is just a joke going
on; it's a drama going on, you see.
People are just thinking
and by reading Zen
and all that, you are
going to achieve something.
You cannot achieve
anything by reading.
Even if you read Bible or Gita,
you cannot achieve anything.
It's only reading!
unclear
[unclear]
All of them are real?  Not one!
You'll find seventy five percent...
A hundred percent!
I have travelled all over the world.
I have been up to Chile,
up to Argentina, up to Colombia.
Except for Australia, I've been everywhere,
but I've met many Australians
and I can tell you, I haven't met one
one sect, which has anything of
truth left in them. Not one sect!
Leave alone the religion part!
Not even one!
Like people like, in India
there was a very decent one
Vallabhacharya was a great man. I mean he
was like an incarnation like that he was.
His disciples are... I
was amazed that even they were.
When he had just done the same
things that I am telling you,
that  you have to get your realisation,
without realisation....  but they
were also just the same
they are also following, you
see, something that is dead.
You see supposing
you are not realised
and you start doing
Sahaja Yoga to someone
moving your hands like this and raising
the kundalini. What will you do?
You cannot do anything.
So, before,  you see, feeling anything
about what I say, you get your
vibrations all right first of all.
You get yourself Realised
that's the main thing
once your vibrations are all right
then you can judge it better,
because before that you cannot
because there is no rapport with
the truth and with the absolute.
You must get your vibrations corrected.
First your vibrations must be
corrected, you must be realised
and then you must judge
it, otherwise you cannot.
This is why it is, you see, we can spread anything
which is false, because there I don't
have to put a condition on you,
here you have to be realised
and you have to be settled down
then only you'll understand
without that... by paying money,
say by joining any committees or by
becoming any member of it you cannot.
You cannot become a  Sahaja Yogi.
Sahaja Yogi can only become,
if you have got the vibrations,
if you can raise the kundalini, then only
you can be a Sahaja Yogi.
This is a very big condition.
I mean if you are some sort of a society
as you have Buddha society [unclear]
you can have, say, a church
or a temple or any society
anybody can join.
You can join it, but you
cannot be called that.
And this has to be,
because of this problem
A person like Christ
has been brought and
thrown up to dust;
a person like Buddha,
a person like Mahavira
all incarnations. They were very great,
too great for human beings to understand.
And because they never got realisation,
they just brought them to dust.
Absolutely to dust!
Buddhism has taken such divergency
If you go to Ladakh....
Tibet! These Lamas! Now see the Lamas,
it is not what you call as Buddhist.
Some of the Lamas are not
Buddhists at all. They're just
heads of their community.
They are not religious people.
But they are not Realised.
I have not yet met even one
Lama who's realised.
You know this Panchen Lama and
these, what is?  Dalai Lama!
They are politicians
I'll tell you they are politicians;
a hundred percent and not only
but they are possessed people.
[unclear]
You see apart from that
they're possessed, you see,
that's how they get their third
eye and all this nonsense and
they got those visions and things.
I was... my husband was
with Lal Bahadur Shastri
and Lal Bahadur Shastri's
wife was a little shy lady
and in the end she did not go out.
Normally I used to attend to people.
and I used to sit next to them.
So this, when this Dalai
Lama and this Panchen Lama
came to Delhi, I was
sitting next to him.
I just could not sit. I was
getting such burning from him.
I felt a little nervous sitting
next to him, I mean funny.
So Shastriji asked me, "Why
are You not happy there?"
I said, " If you permit me
this man is not religious."
"Can you sit me....  He recognised me.
He said, "Yes please if you want
you can sit on the other seat."
So I moved on and then I gave
him bandhan and all that.
They are parasites apart from anything.
You see, Tibet people are so poor,
so poor. Have you been to
Tibet? Very poor people!
So poor you cannot imagine,
the poorest of poor are there.
And these people live in complete
luxury in palaces like that.
They take their milk in silver bowls.
They have marble inlets
and the people are living
in absolutely, dire poverty.
They do not have houses, you
know they have thatched things.
I mean, you cannot imagine
the poverty there.
However those people to suck
the blood and live like this,
it is only possible for
the rakshasas, I tell you.
If you do not like
it, I have to say that.
You will feel the same
way if you are sensitive.
I've been to Brindavan, to Gokul
and I came back and I told
them all the rakshasas,
all the Kamsas and the anucharas,
the servants of Kamsa,
all the rakshasas
are now the Pandas.
Now you may not like it.
When Christ hit people with
a hunter they did not like it,
but that does not mean
they do not deserve it.
The river Ganges lashed
its anger this time.
All the Pandas had to run away.
You see, they're the people who are
making money on the river Ganges.
Sitting there looting people.
How can it please God?
It is anti God, absolutely anti God.
Absolutely! Hundred percent!
Whether people like it or not
I have to say the truth.
I'm not here for seeking elections.
All these are to be punished
and have to be thrown
away from the society.
These are the ones who crucified Christ.
These are the ones who hit Buddha.
These are the ones
who tortured Mahavira.
These are the people who are today
become... You have religious people
trying to propagate religions and trying
to make money out of it.
Very ingenious method
to build up a religion
to earn money.
It's floating an enterprise.
I agree with you but what
that might [unclear]
My interest in Buddhism is not in
Buddhist, but the philosophy of Buddha.
That's what is Sahaja,
means nothing but Sahaja.
So therefore then, what
was the criticism?  Because you see...
It's not about Buddha.
I never say...
How can I criticise Buddha, I mean we
use Him for  clearing our Agnya.
You see how can I criticise. It would be
saying tomorrow that I'm criticising Christ.
I mean how could I criticise Him?
How could this idea go
into your head.  Never!
How can I criticise him?
On the contrary I'm criticising those
who are using him for their own purpose.
[unclear]
That's it!
They said that every spiritual leader, you know, even Mahatma Gandhi, he has been so abused,
and he hasn’t been dead very long.
[Unclear}
Yes, but somebody has to say it.
Somebody has to say
these things. Isn't it?
Somebody has to speak
out and say it's wrong?
Yes, you see, you all... you see I'm giving
words to what you feel within yourselves.
Isn't it?
That's what... How can I criticise something
that is my part and parcel in My Being?
How could you think like that?
Hello Sweet!   Hello Sir!  It's good
Look at that!
So you don't be dragged
into these things. You see,
this is a very important thing that
you must all get your Realisation.
All of you must get
Realisation because of this,
this one snag.
One snag in all these
religious leaders.
This snag has done all the harm.
You see, Buddha was
absolutely correct, but
that was not the time
for giving Realisation to people
So he thought that if
he organises people
they will be ready to
receive their Realisation.
That's what he organised you see
and that's how he created a Sangha,
but as all people are..
I was also just the same
because I had to learn
a lot about human beings.
You know these people are too pure to
understand how human beings are crooked.
Even, you see, some
them have said that
you must not tell lies,
you must not do this,
you must not do this.
It's useless for human beings.
If you tell them, immediately
they will take a Bible
or have a congregation,
have a church nicely
and give lectures.
"You should not tell lies, these
are Ten Commandments,
Christ came in and He's our
Father."  He's this and that.
Go home and do the same thing,
and take all the money from the people.
This Tukarama we had
we had very great
saints like Gyaneshwara
Take the greatest of all
is Adi Shankaracharya,
the one who came, you see. He
did not come to refute Buddha.
He came to refute Buddhism.
The way the Buddhism was going
and what he said was exactly
the same as Buddha said.
Exactly the same
He said, "Na Yoge Na Sankhya."
"Neither by yoga nor by sankaya is
this kind of [unclear]."
And by doing all this 'sanghshakti'
and all that. Nothing!
Only by Mother's Grace,
that it will work out.
and that one has to get
Realisation. He said
so clearly, but you will find
hardly few Indians,
who are supposed to be Hindus, reading
Shankaracharya. Can you believe it?
So, what’s the use of reading
it? “Only praise the Mother!”
That’s what he said. People asked Him,
“Why have You praised
the Mother only?
Why don’t you write
something else?”
He said, “That’s the
only way you can get it.
What’s the use of giving
all avidya,
non-knowledge?
I am giving the real knowledge: you
praise the Mother and just do it.”
And all those learned
pandits and all that,
they challenged him,
and they tortured their lives.
Now what is the present Shankaracharya
Shringari doing, do you know that?
This Shankaracharya took a sanyasa
because He had to work
and dedicate Himself,
and He went all over the world
whenever it was possible for Him. He
went to Kashmir and all these places,
and He did such a lot of work.
While this fellow who is a
small little, horrible thing,
he is now making
whether you like it or not,
I will have to say this.
He is trying to collect money because
he has to make an umbrella of gold.
And he has to put diamonds on that,
and there is  seven
stones will be put,
and nine stones will be
put on that umbrella
and one day, when he will be sitting,
the umbrella is going  to fall off.
I have a feeling all this doesn't matter
because  the truth is what matters, and
the truth is the hardest thing to find
Yes, that's it!
So, he will finally [unclear]
But, but – you see, a truth can only,
can be found when you remove the clouds!
The clouds will move.
No, no, no, no, that you
have to remove yourself.
[unclear] the benefit ...
No, no! You can.
So, therefore…
You see, it is your own
mind that forms the cloud.
If you are on the truth,
the clouds will disappear
but you must tell people
there are clouds,
you have to tell them. Not
only – you have to tell them
the fact, because you see,
we are getting people here
from different sources and
different types, you see?
I have been facing people in Japan. For
example, I faced lots of Zen people
and I have to talk to them.
Some of them did accept,
and some of them did not.
What can I do about it?
[unclear ] You can't prevent people from
making clouds like poor seekers. So...
You see the poor seekers
are taken advantage of.
Yes, but you can’t prevent that, so therefore,  you
don't allow it to block your way,  you just walk round.
That’s very nice to say, but
it  doesn’t happen that way.
They block your way because they
are in your sub-conscious.
You have to face it. You have to take
them out, you have to cleanse them.
With Sahaja Yoga – what happens? That
you can see it and you can clear them.
But if you just say, “Now I am  Realised."
"Oh it’s all right." It is not so.
It is not so!
That’s why they did in,
in the ancient time
the Hatha-Yoga style was first
to take a person from childhood
away from the madding crowd,
keep him there, cleanse him,
keep him in pure conditions
and treat him very well
and then give him a  Realisation,
gradually from one chakra to
another chakra and take him up
for..  this was done in many ages,
in many lives of those people.
They were again selected,
brought in, and again it was done.
It was a very long process.
But now, after getting  Realisation,
you can do it yourself.
You can clear yourself, clean yourself,
but you must face what
sorts of problems there are.
Now for some people here,
I mean most of them,
They have no this
problem anymore now.
They do not think that
these Buddhist and anyone of them,
whether Lamas or Damas or anything,
they have any contribution
made towards spiritual life.
They are convinced of it.
They do not contribute
anything to spiritual life.
These children do,
such  Realised soul,
it’s a  Realised soul.
Now if he is a  Realised soul
and if the, if the head of the Zen is not,
what can you do about it?
It’s a fact.
And those who follow Zen are not following
because they have to be  Realised.
First thing is they should be  Realised, and who
will  Realise them if the head is not  Realised?
If one light is not enlightened, how
is it going to enlighten other lights?
Anyway Mataji  the thing is
that after you have been  Realised,
if you've got Realisation from You  if
you go anywhere near people like that.
It’s not like it was before, you really
face it and really I ought to know that...
Ha!  Now you better tell
them Sheila about yourself.
You see, you are sticking on to this. Now just
tell what happened to you  Sheila, you tell them.
There is just one point. Maybe she has
to go the long way round to come to..
No, no, no, no, no, no, no!
The point is....
It is not. Now I tell you that.  It
is, – you are saying this, that
you people all believe that you are
all guided that way. You decide.
You see, you can seek  guidance, but
nobody is going to force you that way.
It’s your own choice.
You make mistakes through your choice,
your freedom is all the time there.
What I can do is to tell you what is what
and leave it to your freedom.
That if you think that, if everybody
has to go, then why should I be here?
No,  I didn't say they'd  have to go but
when once that
people make  a choice
to seek, they are not going to just
walk straight into the open door,
they are going to crash
into the wall on the way.
So therefore people who come
to You finally will be Yours.
They would do that...
Yes, they do. Yes I agree
Yes they do, I have all the
patience, I know, I have that,
I have all the patience
for them, but what My
thing, My job is to tell them, this is
a wall, now you don’t hit your head.
And being a Mother, you can imagine, I
see them as little babies now newly born.
So I feel concern and I tell them very positively, very clearly that don’t jump into that fire.
But still they do, some
of them, Sheila did that.
Absolutely, I said to
Gregoire this morning
although we know that you
haven't got chilli we think
I know Mataji told me that that will burn me
but I'm just going to put one finger
in a little bit to make sure
and once it's burnt you, you know, like you
never.. I mean it just freaks you out completely..
She didn’t identify at all, she
just visited them once. Once only!
I was very ill, physically and everything
an [unclear}  which was being
run by him, though he  wasn't there.
I don’t like doing the same thing.
[unclear]  Muktananda! A good job.
Just imagine
[unclear]
And now you see the people from
Muktananda,  now just see My position is,
they come from Muktananda
here, so many of them.
I cleanse them, I clean
them, I put them right.
I tell them whatever it is, why they are
sorry, what's the problems, how it happens.
I mean, I have to work really, really
very hard for them, really very hard,
and then they again go into  some trap.
So it... I have to point it out very clearly,
that as long as you are
identified with falsehood
you will not be  Realised.
You cannot get it.
You have to give up falsehood,
see for yourself, work it out!
The best judgement: your vibrations!
You must get it. Now see this girl
has been reading certain books and
things and that’s gone  on her head
and she herself can feel it that
there is a blockage  in her head.
You can feel it yourself, isn’t it?
If the sensitivity is all right,
then you go to the right point.
But no, you see, your sensitivity is
very much blurred and constricted.
Still there, come here! Now ask
Me other questions, all right?
So it is for your own good,
your own good and I’ll tell you. I am not
telling even one thing that is not auspicious
and I will not,  whether
people like it or not.
So sometimes I camouflage,
because things do not go
straight into their heads.
As I told, that if somebody is stupid,
you shouldn’t say, “You are stupid.”
Yes!
One has to go in a round way.
That’s a Mother’s style.
But I have to tell you the truth,
I am telling you the truth.
First thing you should do, is
to establish your vibrations.
First thing is that,
then you talk about it.
You should say, "Nothing
doing, first my vibrations.
There are so many people
who have established here.
Why have I not yet?,
Why not? I must get it.”
That’s the thing, should be there.
If that works out …
it’s very good. If it doesn’t work out,
then work it out. That’s the only thing
you have to get it, nothing else.
Is to understand.
Now I asked her what books did she read.
What happened? She told Me, you see.
So, I can now correct it, I know
where is the problem, you see.
By telling Me facts, what is the
problem, I can correct it better.
Like a doctor is to be
told, what is the thing.
Because most of the things,
here in the West, is mental.
Our reading, our – you see – past life
and all these things in the
sub-consciousness has come
and also our ambitions and
our aspirations and all that.
All these things work out, [unclear]
So, we have to clear ourselves, we
have to be absolutely cleared out.
This is what Buddha wanted,
is enlightenment, what else?
Did He want you people to form
societies?  Nothing of the kind!
He wanted only to get enlightenment,
to be able to read themselves
and not some books, you see.
Buddha wrote no book.
Nothing He wrote, and those who write
about Him were not Realised  people either.
He said that you should
not worship anything,
because He was so fed
up with the people
who were worshipping
all kinds of nonsense.
So He said, ‘don’t  worship’. Now they
are worshipping his tooth, his hair,
his nails, this, that. Of course,
to Me, I know, it is great.
Everything has a meaning, but to
these people it has no meaning.
They cannot feel the vibrations of
that, so what are they worshipping?
Like in Kashmir I went, and I went to a
place and I just got tremendous vibrations
and I said, “What’s there here?
Is there a temple or something?”
They said no. I said, “This place
seems to be really vibrated.”
I stopped the car and asked the driver.
He said, “You know there is a 'ek bal' that
is the one hair of Mohamed is put there."
” Oh, I said, that’s great!”
And the driver said,
“What’s great? This hair has
caused so much problem here.
People have been fighting over it, there
has been so many murders in this place.”
Now what the poor hair has
done? You see, just imagine.
To Me, it has given Joy and
such feeling of oneness there.
And to others it has given fighting.
The Muslims have been fighting, because
the hair was lost and this and that.
Then, when the hair was returned,
they did not know whether it was
a true hair or some other hair …
Big controversies about things!
We went to...  there is one place of
Valmiki-Ashram near Bihar, you see.
On the other side of Bihar in Nepal
and I went down there, you see, wading
through a river to see that place.
Just to feel it, I know it is that.
So then when I came
back, and see, one of the
very learned men from
Bihar, he was also there.
He said, “Mother, what do you think, is
this the place where Sita-ji lived?”
I said, “Yes, She did. She did.” He said,
“How do You know?” I said, “I know it,
for one thing, it’s My own
experience that it was so.
Apart from that, you can
ask any Sahaja Yogi,
they can say, that this is the place She lived,
because you feel the vibrations throughout.”
He said, “Really there are books
and books written against it,
that this is not the place,
it's on the Indian soil,
not on the Nepali soil, this, that,
all these things … Just imagine!
They are  fighting
about the Divine Mother
whether She was born
in Nepal or here.
She was a Nepali-Lady, She was
born in Nepal, no doubt about it.
But Nepal is no good,
they are no good, neither Indians are.
All are just the same. Horrible people,
fighting anything good you
bring in, they start fighting.
What to do with this human nature?
Actually, these people did not realise
none of them knew,  as
I know you people.
Really I can tell this.
Even Christ did not know
how human beings are crooked.
They are too good.
Humanisation has to be completed I think
in this life of Mine, and I get horrified!
Still people think I am
ignoramus, I don’t know much.
I have to still read lots of
things to understand human beings.
You see, because of their so-called
intelligence, which cheats them,
because they think, you
know, they can manage,
they think they can manage everywhere.
What they are not
managing is themselves,
their own joys, their own properties,
their own wealth – that’s
what they are not managing,
that’s what they are not feeling,
that’s what they are missing.
That is within them, so great,
bubbling,
manifesting, anxious to come out,
that’s all missing.
Now what are they
managing like fools?
Is out of show!
Somebody has to say it
and can convince you.
I am here to convince;
I am here to convince you,  about Buddha.
And do you know Buddha
took His birth again?
He was Hassan and Hussein, one of them
was Buddha, another was Mahavira.
See the silence.
Buddhist won’t accept,
because they got fright of their life,
the way the Buddhist were on [unclear]
Mohammed Sahib took
His birth as Nanaka.
If you read Nanaka’s
life, I mean if you read
what He has to say, all
the time He is saying,
“Oh God, how are you fighting among
yourselves, the Hindus and the Muslims,
or the Muslims and the other people?
I am just the same!
How are you fighting?”
You see, when He died, Mohammed Sahib
and  He saw where the religion
was taken by Muslims,
He was to be born again.  To tell them!
But when He was born again,
and He started telling,
people stoned Him.
And these Sikhs ask them,
these fools, you go and ask them,
“What He has done?”
All His life He was trying
to unite both of them
because He was so much
surprised at this.
And imagine  the Sikhs, all their
lives they are fighting the Muslims,
and the Muslims, the fools,
they are fighting the Sikhs.
I talked to some Arab ladies.
They agreed with Me.
There are  so many
who agree with Me,
you can see, after all they
are intelligent enough to see.
But something of it lurks in
us which must be taken out,
which is falsehood. You must
give up all that is falsehood,
because falsehood keeps
you away from reality
which is beauty and joy,
which is yourself.
When I talked in
nineteen-seventy first time
and then I had to lash all of them
I called it spiritual jugglery.
"Left and right all of them," I said,
Then  everybody was so frightened.
There was one Raja of Mundi,
he came, he said, “Mother
they will go, come and kill You.” I said,
“This time I am going to kill them.
Nobody is going to crucify Me
now. Don’t you worry about Me”
He said, “We are worried about your
well being. You are saying like this, you see,
people will feel very
angry with You.”
I said, “Let them come.
This time I am going to face it.
It was all right before I put up a show,
but now no more.
Let’s have it out."
Somebody has to say it.
It’s  very nice for Me to go about,
"Oh [unclear] I love you, Oh very good,
In this society is very good.
That church is very good.
Pope, you're My love." And all that!
And get all of them together,
because I am a Realised
Soul no doubt,
and I can say that, “Oh I am
this, I have got curative powers,
I am raising Kundalini”
and this and that,
and get all of them put together.
I could have done that way, but
it is not going to work out.
Of course, if they come to Me,
I’ll manage,
because there is a certain
protocol of the truth.
Christ did not go to these
people and tell them.
He argued with them and told
them, what was the truth.
Buddha preached non-violence,
He thought that by non-violence
methods, these people will accept.
But He found that by doing that,
what has happened, all the horrible
rakshasas are sitting there, very nicely.
Anybody who is a good
person is to be tortured,
that was the lot.
Anybody who is a religious
person must be killed.
Anybody who was a Realised
Soul must be crucified.
This was the pattern of life.
So, they came as Hassan and
Hussein, and fought it!
If the time comes,
the wrath of God will
come upon these people.
He has a very tremendous wrath.
If in one incarnation
if it has not shown, it
doesn’t mean it does not exist
It does exist.
It’s all right for Christ to say, that
if you put...   if somebody
slaps you on one face,
put the other around.
It is just to develop your patience,
but when you slap on one face
of a  Realised Soul, one side is cleared
and when you put the other cheek,
the second side is also cleared.
Both the sides are just cleared out,
that’s why it was said.
The deeper sense is like that.
And then the person falls at your
feet, asking for forgiveness.
Just see, a wasp bit Me here and the
vibrations were  a hundred times more.
Isn’t it a funny thing?
It is a very deep  secret of  life,
but at least you must know that,  unless and
until you  give  up all that is falsehood,
which keeps you floating
on the surface,
you cannot go deep down.
These are all bubbles, you know,
you must have seen people floating
with two,
two balloons  jetting out, you see.
In the same way, our ego and
superego keeps you floating.
It doesn’t allow you to go
deep down into yourself.
So by rationality you
cannot understand it.
You give up your rationality,
come deep down in the centre.
You have to move there.
Buddha did His job; He built  up here,
left hand side,  your personality.
Mahavira did His job here.
Now it’s  My job to do it, is to break
your Brahmarandra and let Me do it.
They are all within Me, They
are part and parcel of Me,
I'm theirs and they are mine;
every minute, every second,
every moment they are here.
Don’t worry about Me.
Don’t  worry about yourself.
You just think how far you have
gone with your meditation,
how deep you have
gone into your Self.
If you have not gone, it’s
not a mistake of Sahaja Yoga,
but is your own mistake.
It is something wrong
somewhere. Just ...
where is the mistake?  Is your ego  bloating
up  or is your super-ego  bloating up?
What is not clear with you?
Dive into your being?
See now, how much I am
working hard on you
days in and days out.
It is a simple thing.
In India, we had someone
who belonged to a big organisation, and he
came round, and he started arguing out.
So,
one of the Sahaja Yogis asked,
“Now come and tell me, how many people
you have given realisation to,
how many people you have cured?”
He said, "None."
Then he said, “What are
you talking to Mataji?
She has given realisation to
thousands, you have seen it.
She has cured thousands of people,
we have cured also,
so better take it
from Her instead of
getting angry with Her and telling Her
about this big organisation that you have.”
When the fellow was changed,
and when he went and told his organisation
people, who were following him as a guru,
they said, “Oh, he is gone
mad.” They left him,
and they selected another
mad man to be their guru.
Nobody is going to stand by you,
organisation-wise, I can tell you. All
your organisations will never accept Me
as a guru, never.
Because they stand
on some falsehood.
They will never accept
Me, the whole of it.
None of these organisations
are going to accept Me.
In America, I have
seen the same thing.
It is a sad thing, but
it is the same thing.
There is one lady who is running, she
calls it “Light of the Universe.”
She invited Me there, and she [unclear]
She  arranged for Me a three days
conference and all that, you see.
At the end of it  she took
Me down into her house,
down  below, and  there
she had made a temple
and all full of bhoots
and she said, “Here I call
my master from Tibet.”
I said, “Very nice, and
why have you called Me?”
I put a bandhan to her and
all that. I came away.
So, some people left her
completely, to join Me.
She was writing to Me
that, I should go to her,
and again I have to speak  because
she makes a lot of money out of that.
But I told her not to
meet for some time.
So the whole of it
won’t come to Me,
because the basis is wrong,
the basis is wrong,
absolute falsehood it is.
The basis of all these organisations is wrong.
It has done no good, if you see it very
clearly and honestly, they had done no good.
At the most they are
philanthropic things,
like, we can say, a council
which is rendering help
to some sick people,
to admit in the hospital, some
this and that, that’s all.
At the most, if they
have done anything.
So, you are like councilmen,
you see, council people.
But why bring in God there?
It’s all right, you are social
workers, do the social work.
That  is not spiritual work.
Spiritual work is spiritual work,
where you have to be awakened.
You understand?
So, all those societies or all
those religions, all of them,
one and all, hundred percent.
You are saying twenty-five percent,
I would say even if one percent
is there, I’ll thank My stars.
Even one percent, I've not seen
a genuine one which is based on
giving  Realisation to people
in the real sense of the word.
This so called, this  Daya Mata's
place, I have been there.
This Yogananda was
not a  Realised Soul,
you will be shocked that  ‘Babaji
and ‘Dadaji’ and all of them
were not Realised Souls at all.
Now the people who were
there have come and told Me.
You see they, there was a doctor
we had, he died of that.
He used to do all the  Khechari,
he used to take... cut his tongue,
put it back, put it here, you see.
Imagine all these things
and always his tongue
used to wag  like that,
and he had to put some sort of a
hold for his tongue. Otherwise the
tongue would wag out like that.
He had cut it through his thread
and turned it up, put it here
for raising the Kundalini. Just imagine!
Now if somebody comes like
that, what should I say,
“Now you cut your nose
and put it inside?”
Just tell Me!  There
are people like that.
This  Yogananda’s school,
they are doing Khechari
Kabira came, and He lashed them,
completely this
Khechari and all that.
He said, “One day your
tongue will be cut,
your noses will be cut
and this will happen.
You will be hanging down
head downwards in the hell,
the way you are treating these
people, those who are seeking.”
These are the people, and
they publish books, you see.
Their books will be published
and all that, they will have BBC-Programs
and everything will support
them and help them, because
they are all based on falsehood.
What did they do to Christ?
Did any scientist accept Him?
Did any bureaucrat accept Him?
What did they do to Buddha?
When He lived, He
had a very bad time.
After His death of course everybody
started making money and things like that.
But what good  have they done?
Japanese supposed to be the most
as you say Japanese are Buddhists.
Cruellest people ever known!
Cruellest people are Japanese.
Cruellest of all, you see,
they have such a funny system.
I went to Japan; I was amazed
that any good-looking woman
does not marry in Japan.
This has come out of Buddhism,
just imagine, a system.
No good-looking
woman would marry,
neither an educated
only dishwashers marry.
The women who are absolute useless,
good for nothing, ugly
looking horrid women
who are maidservants
in other places,
they marry, and they are the
mothers of the children of Japan.
The mother,
even if her husband beats her,
does anything, has to bear,
he can make keeps in the
house, concubines there,
he can go and visit the Geishas, she
is not supposed to say anything.
And that’s why in the
whole world, you know,
a Japanese wife is the best.
She is worse than a slave.
And if you go to Japan, nobody will
invite you to their houses and homes.
See I went without My husband, so they
didn’t know what to do about Me, you see.
They couldn’t take
Me to Geisha houses,
and they couldn’t take Me
to their houses either.
So, they didn’t know really
what a pickle I was.
And I read, they didn’t know
what to really make out of Me.
I told them I would like to
go to Geisha houses also,
to see there what’s happens.
And there I found with these Geishas,
when I was talking to them,
that they are fed up
of this nonsense.
They said, you see, “We
are beautiful women,
so we don’t marry,
because we get the money.
And we are part-time,
also career girls.”
There were some part, part-time
Geishas and part-time career girls.
And they all meet in there.
You see, they are
absolutely openly like that.
Here they do it also, I mean the
way the women go out for dating.
Is what? Is Geisha business!
Dating is what?
I mean there they call themselves at
least honestly, they are Geishas,
but here dating with a man, poor man
has to pay for them every evening,
when it is too much.
All this is in a very subtle way here.
So you see, you say there is no
prostitution and there is prostitution.
I mean, they said, what are
the laws of prostitution.
You cannot,  sort of advertise it, but
you can have a sauna bath or something.
I mean, some sort of a thing that they
have made here with their intelligence.
But in Japan it is clear-cut,
Geisha is a Geisha,
a housewife is a housewife,
but if you see a housewife,
her hands,
there is no softness, really hard
hands, just like the bark of a tree.
If you see the feet,
if you see their legs are
bent, their bodies are bent,
very young women look so older.
We were invited to a
very rich man’s house.
There I saw his daughters-in-law
were beautiful, but
they had to pay a lot of money to those
girls and to their parents to get them there.
No girl would marry.
Then the children, when they see
their mother being treated like this,
what will happen to them?
You see, after all, there is a mother’s pride
within them, and they can’t bear it anymore.
So Japanese are the people, outside
they are very  disciplined,
you see, they are like the way
the mother is disciplined outside.
They’ll go on bowing you.
See, if you don’t stop, they’ll bow on.
If you stop it, then they will stop.
They will not stop earlier, but if
there is an accident they’ll get down,
bow to each other.
But in the crowd,
if they find a foreigner,
they will put their heels [unclear.]
They kill people in
such a butchery way,
they are butchers, I tell you!
They are very disciplined, because
one is talking, nobody will talk.
They are just like machines.
Hiroshima gave them a shock,
that really gave them a
shock, and they were jolted.
The young people now, the young
women are revolting against it,
they are realising it.
I don’t know the way sometimes the
young go on to another mad, crazy day.
But there is an awakening in Japan.
Now you can’t blame Buddha for this,
you cannot blame
Bodhidharma for this,
the Zen-man who did this.
He was a  Realised
Soul, no doubt about it.
They do not understand
anything about  Zen,
they do not.
They said, “This is all
very difficult for us.”
They have certain
things like no place
which I went and saw Myself,
which I really enjoyed.
They couldn’t understand
why I was enjoying it.
They couldn’t understand why I
enjoyed their temples very much,
what it was to convey,
you see.They have Temples
which create like, you
can say, a Moss-Temple
is on top of a hill, you see.
you have to go through a
building, on top of a hill.
When you come out there is a
little place, like that only,
[unclear] this one, and there is a little
mount made like a, like a drop, you see?
And a little drop here, like
a question-mark, you can say,
or a  drop here.
And this all  filled with
small plants of moss.
You can see it through the,
through the, what do you call them
the  magnifying glass, beautiful different,
different , you see, mosses are there.
Now, anybody will say, “What’s this?
All the way to brought us
here, what is all this?
Is it a Temple? What
sort of a Temple?”
Now that is a Zen-style,
that when you see it, you
cannot answer why, how!
You just stop there in
thoughtless awareness.
It was to awaken your
So the Zen-people said, “Now
You tell me what is this?”
I said, “Is it what Zen has told you.
This is what, which, should
not make you talk and think!
You just say that, ‘You watch this”
and do not ask any questions,
become one with it.”
That’s what the
Zen-people tried to do.
They thought that by doing
this, by telling people that,
“Watch this without thought,
watch this without thought”,
it will work out. But they did not know
that these people were not even awakened.
It’s only possible for
people who are awakened.
They were of that high,
they did not realise,
that these people were not even awakened,
how can they do things without thought.
And all these temples are
useless for these  people.
There is another place
where there is lot of
sand  spread out,
and a beautiful pattern drawn on it
and there are some stones
of various forms put there
and you have to go sit
around it and see that.
Everybody who goes there  they
said, “Mad people these are.”
They take you to a temple,
and there  you see all these
and one  American  said,
[unclear]
I lost  my feet, and what’s this?
What is it?” And nobody
can understand,
the Zen-people, don’t understand,
you see,  This is what it is.
“Very beautiful, you must see,
this is very beautiful,”
they are telling in their funny English,
to these Americans, [unclear,
and they say]  really?
And they have to walk bare-feet,
you see, all the way down.
They can’t understand why all
this circus was done for them,
and the ones who is  explaining
do not know. They do nothing
but the same thing,
that you watch a thing,
which does not communicate anything
to you, so you become quiet.
Then they start comparing
as usual about ideas are,
that –  “Oh!  This is like an ocean and
in the ocean, there are these boats.”
“It’s rather not like
a boat, I must say.”
The another one  with
some other idea,
that this is this, this is this
but that is the thing,
you don’t have to do!
You don’t have to compare it with anything,
you just have to see it, without thought!
That’s what Zen wanted to do, to watch
a flower without thinking of it,
just watch it as it is.
How can you do it unless and
until you are thoughtlessly aware?
And he didn't...  they did not know that
people are not thoughtlessly aware.
That’s possible only when  the
Kundalini is above the Agnya.
They thought minimum that
must be with human beings,
you see, that they are thoughtlessly,
they can become thoughtlessly aware.
They did not know that
that is also missing,
because they were of a
very high-quality people.
All of them were born Realised,  actually.
Twenty-six of them in six
centuries! Can you believe it?
Sixth century it started,
till the twelfth century there were
twenty-six, after that there was not one Kasha.
Is a fact, it is written down. I
mean, I’m  not telling you a lie.
So, who can explain what is what?
It’s  in every religion, in every book
all this nonsense has  been done.
Blind explaining something that is light.
It’s an impossibility!
I do not blame them for that,
but I blame them there,  that they think, “Oh, we
are the enlightened.  Oh, we are the Buddha.
We, we, –  know everything,
we are Christ!”
Christians think, they are all Christians;
means they are Christ themselves.
This mis-identification is very wrong.
Do you understand now?
This is what it is.
You said all the Buddhist,
all the Buddhists I know
never say that
enlightenment comes easy.
It could take a thousand lives.
That’s, that’s the best way
of deluding people, you see.
It takes thousand times,
it’s correct. At what time?
When they were Zens’, it was
very difficult, but not today.
It was very difficult at the
time of My grandmother’s time
to think even that you
will go to the moon.
And even when people went
there, she would not believe it.
She said, “No, no – you are just
showing a picture, just befooling me.
How can anybody go?”
Even if you showed her anything,
she would not believe.
She said, “It’s all there,
coming to the earth
and this is what you are just there,
just befooling you, don’t believe them.
They must be befooling.”
Even today, if you tell her,
she is not going to believe you,
because it was impossible.
Even when I was a student,
you see, they used to say so many million years
and billion years it will take to go to the moon.
It has not taken anything like that.
So, the growth of life,
when it comes, in the
beginning one flower appears,
a second appears after
three, four years,
then when the tree comes up and
when the blossom-time comes,
so many flowers come up.
This is a living thing.
First one fish became a reptile,
then after many years
second one came in,
but after some time
shoals of them became.
It’s the evolutionary way.
What they said, was
correct at that time,
is not correct today.
Because they say it, are you going to stop
your  Realisation, even if you are getting it?
For them, it is impossible, not difficult,
but it is an impossibility,
they can never get  Realisation.
So what they say, there is truth in it.
It’s difficult – these Lamas never!
None of them, not one of them
is going to get  Realisation.
Take it from Me. Not one!
I am not defending now
these organisations at all,
I agree with you. I'm only.....
I am just  telling you, I am not addressing
it to you, but in general, you see?
I am just saying a general statement.
Part of it is of course
your mind that is speaking.
[unclear] and also gave Me clarification.
These Lamas are parasites,
absolute  parasites.
Living on other people’s money, opium.
Other people’s money,
dealing in opium, it’s the best trade.
All  leading an abnormal life  and
doing all kinds of abnormal things.
They've never  given any
guidance to the whole world.
It's all guidance how they could
live without spending any money.
First of all, it is difficult to give  Realisation,
you can see that.
Then, when you give them also,
they again go down in to it.
Then again bring them out,  again they go,
again deep down.
If it is not working out, it is not working out.
Now as it is, if you say that,
“My left hand is tingling”
I am not telling you that, you are
saying that, it is happening to you
it is definitely there. So, there is
something wrong. So, you must cure it,
it’s a simple thing.
I am not giving any auto-suggestions
that your right hand is paining,
or left hand is heavy. It is there, and it is
there and you, yourself, you are telling Me.
So, what I am trying to do is
to help you out, take it out.
And it is not so easy also for you.
It’s better?
Hmm, it’s good.
This hand is so cold and
this one's really hot.
Ha, see now, she herself is telling Me.
This one is so cool and this one is so
hot. Now I am not telling her anything.
(Shri Mataji is rubbing Her hands.)
Hmm. Put your hand here down.
Right hand on this side.
You see, one hand is cold, one
hand is hot. How do you explain?
You cannot.
Mataji, yesterday in the seminar one of the
things we didn’t know much about was the Void,
because it seemed a very
important part of it,
the Nabhi and Swadishthana around it,
yet  we didn’t know that much about this .
Hmm, hmm. So, what do you want to know?
Well, I mean  how the
Kundalini passes through it,
because there  [unclear] this
is a difficult thing to bridge.
What is it?
He said, it was the most
difficult thing to bridge .
For them, it was.
Now, what we call Void,
maybe, that’s  because says in the
Zen, Void has a different meaning,
but in Sahaja Yoga, what
part is called as Void?
You see, in Sahaja Yoga
we do call it as Void,
a part of it, but if you want,
you can call it Bhavasagara,
or you can call it by
a  Gap, means there's a Gap,
This is the stomach of a human
being, it is the visceras,
and it has got two
important Chakras, you see,
one is the central one,
which is called as the Vishnu’s Chakra
and the another one is
Swadishthana which is circling it.
The relationship between
the sustaining power that is within us,
which is the evolutionary power,
which gives us this
human form from amoeba,
which is the evolving power within us,
placed in our stomach,
on the solar plexus.
This relationship between this power
and with the five elements ....